Finding aid to the Caroline Dwight Bain papers SSC.MS.00762
Sophia Smith Collection
Caroline Dwight Bain papers
1926-2015
Sophia Smith Collection
Bain, Caroline Dwight
SSC.MS.00762
2.75 linear feet 3 boxes (2 record cartons and 1 full-size legal box)
This collection consists of the personal papers of archival consultant and loyal Smith College alumna Caroline Dwight Bain (1928-2015). Of special note are the letters Bain wrote to her parents while she was working for the Civil Aeronautics Board in Washington, DC, 1944-1945.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These papers were donated by Caroline Bain's son, George Bain, in 2015, with additional items sent in 2017 and 2018.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series. The first contains the materials sent to the archives soon after Caroline Bain's death in 2015; the second contains materials sent to the archives in 2017 and 2018.
Biographical Note
Archival consultant and loyal Smith College alumna, Caroline (Carol) Bush Dwight was born in Cambridge, Massachusetts in 1922, the only child of Henry Williams Dwight and Margaret Cooper Dwight. Until the age of twelve, she lived in Cambridge, attending the Buckingham School (now the Buckingham, Browne and Nichols School) where she would later serve as a trustee and director of development. In 1934, Dwight and her parents moved to Stockbridge, Massachusetts when her father became president of the Housatonic National Bank. She graduated from the Baldwin School in 1940 and Smith College in 1944. Given the demands of World War II on the home front, Smith students were then encouraged to take summer classes so as to accelerate their graduation date. This Carol Dwight did, finishing her course work a semester early. By February of 1944 she and Smith classmate, Harriet (Hatty) Hulbert Ball, were living in a fourth-floor walkup in Arlington, Virginia; Dwight worked at the Civil Aeronautics Board (CAB) and also volunteered at the local USO. In the fall of 1945, she left the CAB and took a position with the Red Cross in Boston for a few months before starting as box office manager for the Boston Symphony Orchestra, what she would later refer to as"her dream job." In 1949, Carol Dwight married Sherwood E. (Joe) Bain and a year later they bought the house in Cambridge, Massachusetts where they lived until 2009, raising two sons and a daughter there. Carol Bain was an active volunteer and club member. When her youngest child started college, Bain returned to college, too, earning her Master's degree in history from Tufts University in 1978. She then did archival consulting for a variety of Boston area institutions including the Massachusetts Historical Society and the Boston Symphony Orchestra. Bain was a loyal Smith alumna, serving as president of the Friends of Smith College Libraries and for many years supported an annual travel-to-collections grant, named in her honor, at the Sophia Smith Collection and Smith College Archives. An avid world traveler and a breeder of purebred dogs, Carol Dwight Bain lived a full life until her death in Exeter, New Hampshire in 2015 at the age of ninety-two.
Other Finding Aids
Detailed container lists and introductions to the papers written by the donor, Caroline Bain's son, are availabe in the first box of each series. These can also be sent to remote researchers upon request.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of Caroline Bain's personal papers including travel journals, correspondence, photographs and other biographical materials. Of special note are the letters Bain wrote to her parents while she was working for the Civil Aeronautics Board in Washington, DC, 1944-1945.
World War, 1939-1945 -- War work; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- Red Cross -- Sources; World War, 1939-1945 -- Women -- Personal narratives, American; Washington, DC; Boston, MA; Stockbridge, MA; Smith College -- Students -- History -- Sources; Civil Aeronautics Board; American Red Cross; Boston Symphony Orchestra; articles; Artifacts; Awards; Biographical notes; Biographical sketches; correspondence; Diplomas; Ephemera; Essays; Invitations; Juvenilia; Lists; memorabilia; Notes; photographs; Programs; Research; Yearbooks; Bain, George; Bain, George
- Caroline Bain personal papers, 1926-2015; 2015-S-0102; 1 linear feet (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of the first accession of materials sent to Smith College in 2015. It includes correspondence, photographs, biographical material, and memorabilia. Of special note are the letters Bain wrote to her parents while she was working for the Civil Aeronautics Board in Washington, DC, 1944-1945.
  Other Finding Aids
  A detailed contents list is in the first box of this series, and can also be sent to remote researchers upon request.
- Travel journals, correspondence and photographs, 1944-2015; 2017-S-0061, 2018-S-0009, 2018-S-0021, 2018-S-0044; 1.25 linear feet (One legal size document box and one record carton.)
  This series consists of travel journals, photographs and personal correspondence sent to the archives in 2017 and 2018.
  - Donor's detailed list and index (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence from Caroline D. Bain, 1949-1966 (Box 1)
  - Books and publications, 1967-1986, undated (Box 1)
  - Passports, New Hampshire State ID and health records, 1971-2005 (Box 1)
  - Personal writings, 1982-2014 (Box 1)
  - Inventory and correspondence related to the Norman Rockwell Collection, 2009-2015 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence related to the Caroline D. Bain Fellowship, 2009-2015 (Box 1)
  - Caroline Bain vacation snapshots, 1979-2000; 2018-S-0021 (Box 1)
    Snapshots of people (including Caroline Bain, her husband and their friends) and vistas during vacation trips abroad and to Alaska and Hawaii.
  - Caroline Bain vacation snapshots, 1977-2000; 2018-S-0044; Bain, George; .01 linear feet (1 medium photo envelope) (Box 2)
    Photographs of Caroline Bain and others, primarily snapshots of vacations abroad with her husband; some include other Smith alumnae
    Bain, George
  - Index and journals relating to travels, 1971-2010 (Box 2)
  - Smith College Class of 1944 reunion photographs, 1979-1999; 2018-S-0009 (Box 2)
    Photographs of Caroline Bain and others, mostly at Smith College Class of 1944 reunions.